My goodness, you can almost smell the
beginning of the American Revolution.
But put your patient pants on because we
still have to talk about yet another
cause that led to that great
confilration of liberty and
independence, namely the British
taxation policy. So, if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked, let's get to
it. Okay. Now, if you've been around
this course for more than 5 minutes,
you'll recall that Great Britain did not
view their North American colonists as
the colonists viewed themselves. What I
mean is because of the on-again
off-again policy of salutary neglect,
the American colonies, though they still
thought of themselves as British
subjects, had developed habits of local
self-governance, which seemed to be a
natural consequence of their rights and
privileges. But Great Britain, to put it
mildly, did not share that opinion. To
them, the colonists were there to serve
the interests of their imperial parent
and thus were in no way independent.
But, you know, that conflicting opinion
rarely caused much tension owing to the
fact that Great Britain's distance from
the colonies was so vast that they were
often distracted with larger matters
like, you know, taking over the rest of
the world. Oh, and by the way, if you
want note guys to follow along with this
video and all my videos, check the link
below. Anyway, after the end of the
French and Indian War, Britain was broke
and exhausted and cooked up a plan to
bring those rascally colonies into
submission through a series of policies.
And the chief architect of those
policies was our boy George Grenville,
whom King George appointed as prime
minister. and he got busy developing a
three-part plan to reassert control and
raise revenue in the American colony.
First, Grenville began by enforcing
existing laws that colonists had
routinely flouted on account of salutary
neglect. And chief among those laws were
the navigation acts that restricted
colonial trade to Great Britain alone
and tax goods going through British
port. Second, Granville decided to
continue a handful of wartime policies
after the war was over. And especially
stanky to the colonial nostril was the
Quartering Act, which forced colonial
subjects to house and feed members of
the British military. And look, the
colonists didn't much like feeding and
housing the British soldiers during the
war, but at least they could understand
the need for it. Like, we're fighting
the war, and it's no good to have hangry
and homeless soldiers. So, fine, I'll
change the sheets. But after the war was
over, why in the fresh heck do I still
have British soldiers living in my
house? Well, as it turns out, the reason
that they stayed was to enforce policies
like the Navigation Act. And again, for
colonists who had developed the habit of
self-ruule and semi-independence, this
was about as welcome as the Saja boys
showing up right at the moment when the
honeymoon is nearly sealed. But fear
not, the colonists were not fooled by
the imperial abs. They were ready for a
proper British takedown. Anyway, the
third and most significant part of
Grenville strategy was to persuade
Parliament to enact a series of new
policies and taxes on the colonies that
would help pay down Britain's war debt.
And I'm just going to mention three of
them. First was the Sugar Act of 1764.
Now, this law actually decreased taxes
on items like imported molasses, but it
did increase efforts to collect that
money since colonists had long skirted
the tax by smuggling goods with other
trading partners. Second, you had the
Currency Act also in 1764, and it
mandated that the colonies could no
longer print their own money, but were
required to use British money. And if
you're like, why are the colonist so
saucy about that? Then all I really need
to tell you is that it's kind of
complicated, but the result was that
British merchants benefited from this
policy while colonial merchants suffered
economic hardship because of it. And
then third and most notorious was the
passage of the Stamp Act in 1765, which
was attacks on paper items like
newspapers and diplomas and playing
cards. Now, maybe this doesn't seem like
a big deal to you, but when the
colonists heard about this law, it made
them want to rage quit this entire
colonial relationship. And why says you?
Well, says I. Because, first of all, it
was the first direct tax levied on the
colonies. And that signaled a big shift
from the past. And also because by the
time it passed, many colonists were
already experiencing economic hardship
as a result of the Sugar and Currency
Act. Additionally, and this is most
important, concerns were being raised
that Parliament was taxing American
colonists who had no representation in
Parliament. And that's when the colonist
summed up their grievances with the
pathy little phrase, namely, no taxation
without representation. Now, to
understand the nature of their beef, you
have to remember that because they had
developed habits of self-ruule over
time, colonists believed that
representation must be local. What I
mean is in all the colonies, they had
representative bodies that created the
local laws. And those representative
bodies were made up of people from the
colony itself. And don't forget that the
colonists had had their fill of
enlightenment thought. And so they got
real testy when it seemed like they were
being governed without their consent.
Anyway, the point is there were
precisely no colonists who were members
of parliament and that did not sit well
with the British subjects over here in
America. Like it wasn't necessarily the
taxes that most upset them. In fact, the
emphasis in the phrase is no taxation
without representation. But all this
colonial angst puzzled Grenville. He
argued that the colonists did have
representation in Parliament, namely
virtual representation. And what that
meant was that Parliament represented
the interest of all English subjects,
whether they were living on the mainland
or abroad in a colony. And so the
colonists were like, "Well, Lord
Granville, I hope you're ready for a
virtual smack bottom because that's the
dumbest thing we ever heard." So all
that to say, these policies were more
than a little grievous to the colonist.
And so they united across the board to
resist them. And those protests came in
a variety of flavors. For example,
merchants, traders, and artisans created
groups like the Sons of Liberty and the
Daughters of Liberty who fought for the
repeal of the Stamp Act. Their members
gave impassion speeches and published
pamphlets arguing against British
imperial policy. Furthermore, they were
able to spread their messages rapidly
thanks to committees of correspondence,
which were groups formed throughout the
colonies whose purpose was to share
information about British infringements
on colonial rights. But then some of
those folks got even a little crazier
and assaulted imperial tax collectors.
Some of them they beat and others they
tarred and feathered. Unless you think
that taring and feathering was just a
fun way to make a tax collector look
like a dumb chicken. Here's where I tell
you that this tar was often very hot and
created deep and painful burns on the
victim. Anyway, another example is that
down in Virginia, the House of Burgesses
passed a series of resolutions known as
the Virginia resolves, which condemned
the notion of taxation without
representation. But by far the most
formal colonial protest came in the form
of the Stamp Act Congress, which
convened in 1765. It was made up of 27
delegates from nine colonies and they
formally petitioned parliament to repeal
the Stamp Act because taxation without
representation amounted to tyranny.
However, it is very important to
remember that even at this most formal
of protests, American independence was
not on anyone's minds as a legitimate
solution to this crisis. In fact, in the
delegates minds, they simply wanted to
experience the fullness of their rights
as British citizens, which the current
policies had diminished. Regardless,
widespread boycotts of taxable goods in
the colonies led Parliament to repeal
the Stamp Act and the Sugar Act in 1766.
However, just to remind everyone who was
still in charge, Parliament followed up
with the Declaratory Act which declared
that Parliament could pass any dang law
that they wanted to. Like, just to be
clear, we are not repealing the Stamp
Act because you protested. Like, we're
still in charge and we do whatever we
want. Just making that clear. Anyway,
although this victory showed the
colonist the limits of parliamentary
power, still no one seriously thought of
fighting for independence. Again, for
the most part, everyone's goal was to
remain a British subject without their
rights being diminished. But even though
the colonists could count the repeal of
the Stamp Act a victory, conditions
continued to deteriorate. In 1767,
Parliament passed the Towns and Acts,
which was attacks on various common
items like glass and paint and paper.
And so that got the colonial resistance
machine fired right back up. And this
time, the most effective means of
protest was the boycott of British goods
covered under the act. And that was
pretty smart because doing so deprived
Britain of the very tax revenue that
they needed in order to pay off their
debts. And it's going to be important
for you to know that women played a
significant role in the success of these
boycots. You see, since women were
generally responsible for buying most of
the goods for their household, it fell
to them to find alternatives to imported
British goods. To that end, many women
spun their own clothes instead of buying
imported textiles, and wearing homespun
was a powerful symbol of protest. So,
needless to say, the British attempts to
whip their colonies into submission were
uh not going well. But then a handful of
other events just made things altogether
worse. The first was the Boston Massacre
of 1770. Basically, a small group of
Boston men angry over all the taxation
policies as well as British military
presence in the city began hurling
snowballs and rocks at a group of
British soldiers. And then a shot was
fired, probably on accident, by one of
the soldiers. And at that, the rest of
the soldiers opened fire as well. And in
the end, five Bostononians were killed.
Now, five people killed is five too many
by my reckoning, but I'm not really sure
that that qualifies as a massacre. But
there were some fiery patriots like
Samuel Adams who had a flare for the
dramatic. And so Adams and other members
of the Sons of Liberty quickly spread
news of this event, which they
themselves called a massacre, and used
it as clear evidence of British tyranny.
Not surprisingly, this event and its PR
campaign raised the colonist hackled
something off. And so Parliament faced
tremendous pressure to repeal the town's
acts, which they did with the exception
of the tea tax because they were all
about propping up the East India
Company, whose tea the colonists were
forced to buy. And speaking of taxes on
tea, that leads us to the second
explosive event that created even more
attention, namely the Boston Tea Party.
Now, in 1773, Parliament passed a new
tea act which eliminated the need for
colonial merchants in buying and selling
tea and gave all authority to the
British East India Company. And to be
clear, this law did not raise taxes on
tea. In fact, it decreased taxes on
imported tea. But the colonist saw this
as yet another attempt to control them
and their economy. And so, they resented
the heck out of it. Now, the culmination
of this protest came in the form of the
Boston Tea Party, in which something
like 50 colonists disguised themselves
as American Indians and dumped nearly 50
tons of tea into the harbor. And in case
you're not feeling the full weight of
that, we're talking about destroying tea
that was worth about $1.5 to$2 million
in today's money. And that, ladies and
gentlemen, is how you get an imperial
power like Great Britain all kinds of
huffy. And so in response to said huff,
Parliament passed the Coercive Act in
1774. Basically, these laws closed down
the Boston Harbor until the destroyed
tea was paid for. Additionally, the laws
included a new quartering act which
mandated that colonist house and feed
even more British soldiers who were
being sent to ensure the enforcement of
the coercive acts. Therefore, it's not
hard to understand why in the colonies,
this set of policies became known as the
intolerable acts. Because in the
colonial minds, they represented the
most significant grab for power and
control that they had yet experienced
from Parliament. And yet again, colonial
resentment was boiling over. And I bet
that resentment is going to have some
consequences, but I'll save that for the
next video. Okay, you can click here to
watch my other unit 3 videos, or you can
click here to grab my video note guides,
which are going to help you cram all the
contents of this course firmly into your
brain fold. I'm glad you stopped by, and
I'll catch you on the flipflop. I'm La.